Guide to the Henry Northrup Castle Papers 1863-1942
University of Chicago Library
Castle, Henry Northrup. Papers
1863-1942
5.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Henry Northrup Castle (1862-1895) Journalist and political leader in Honolulu. Attended Oberlin College. The papers contain personal correspondence, college essays and other writings, the personal correspondence of Castle's immediate family, miscellaneous family papers, and typed copies and printer's proofs of a volume of Castle's letters that were edited by George and Helen (Castle's sister) Mead in 1902. Letters include correspondence with George Herbert Mead.
Information on Use
Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Henry Northrup Castle (1862-1895) was born in Honolulu, Hawaii, the son of American missionary parents, Samuel and Mary Castle. After spending all of his youth in the islands, where he attended Oahu College, he came to the United States in 1878 to attend Oberlin College. It was at Oberlin that Castle began a close friendship with George Herbert Mead, which lasted the remainder of his short life.
After working two years in his brother Will's law office in Honolulu following graduation from Oberlin in 1883, Castle studied in Germany and for two years at the Harvard Law School. Mead joined Castle at Harvard, and both men continued their studies in Germany. As intellectual companions, they shared a mutual interest in philosophy and literature, and exchanged lively letters extensively on these subjects.
Castle returned to Hawaii after marrying a German girl, Frida Steckner, and became editor and owner of the Pacific Commercial Advertiser and the Hawaiian Gazette, the principal newspapers in the islands. Frida was tragically killed in an accident in 1890, a month after their daughter, Dorothy, was born. After having married his second wife Mabel Wing in 1892, Castle returned, in 1893, to the United States to attend the Hawaiian Commission in Washington, which was investigating American intervention in the Hawaiian revolution to overthrow Queen Lilinokalani, and to visit George and Helen Mead. Mead had married Castle's sister, Helen, in 1891.
In 1894, Castle, ever in search of knowledge, returned to Germany with Dorothy to continue his studies in Leipzig. When word reached him in December 1894 of a counter revolt by Hawaiian royalists, Castle and his daughter left immediately for the islands on the steamship, Elbe, which collided with a small steamer on January 30, 1895 in the North Sea. Both Castle and his daughter were drowned, and he never was able to see his younger daughter, Elinor, who had been born a month before.
Castle was eulogized as a martyr to the cause of democratic government for Hawaii and a loyal supporter of the new Hawaiian Republic. Additionally, he was a man of unusual intellectual attainments whose friendship was an important influence on the career of George Herbert Mead.
Scope Note
The collection of about 1500 pieces includes Henry Castle's personal correspondence, his college essays and other miscellaneous writings and papers, the personal correspondence of Castle's immediate family, miscellaneous family papers, and typed copy and printer's proofs of a volume of Castle's letters which were edited by George and Helen Mead and privately printed for the Castle family and friends in 1902.
The collection is divided into seven series. Series I: Personal, includes records related to Henry Northrup Castle’s education, his diaries, personal ephemera, and information about the sinking of the Elbe and Castle’s death. Series II: Correspondence, contains letters written by Castle, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The majority of the letters are written to members of Castle’s family. General ingoing and outgoing correspondence between Castle and non-family members is found at the beginning of the series. Series III: Castle Family Correspondence, comprises personal letters from Castle's immediate family, arranged chronologically under the name of each relative, as well as letters received by members of the Castle family. Series IV: Castle Family Papers, includes ephemera related to various members of the Castle family. Series V: Publication of Letters, contains material related to the arrangement, transcription, and publication of Henry Northrup Castle’s correspondence by his sister, Helen Kingsbury Castle Mead, and his brother-in-law, George Herbert Mead. Series VI: Photographs, contains photographs of the Castle family and of Henry Northrup Castle and his daughter, Dorothy. Series VII: Oversize, contains galley proofs for Castle’s published letters.
Most of the original manuscripts of the published letters are included in the collection, as well as many unpublished letters and papers. The decision for or against publication of entire letters seems to have been based on technical problems rather than content, although occasional personal references were deleted. Since George and Helen Mead were responsible for the editing of the correspondence a natural reticence on their part seems to have motivated the withholding of scattered comments about their private lives. The original letters should always be consulted in preference to the published text to make certain that nothing of importance has been deleted. The original edited letters are always marked in blue pencil. Unpublished letters have the symbol "O" at the top of the first page or were not marked by the Meads.
(Persons interested in Mead will find references to him beginning with Castle's letters of the Oberlin period (c.1979-1883). Mead is most often mentioned, or entire letters are most often addressed to him, during the time when Castle was urging him to come to Harvard (c.1886-1887), and when the two friends were in Germany together (c.1893-1894). Letters to and from Helen Castle Mead after 1891 also reveal information about the philosopher(s early career.)
Fourteen personal letters from Mead, all unpublished, are found in the collection, but much of the correspondence addressed to Castle, other than personal family letters, is not included, and its present whereabouts is unknown. It can be assumed that this correspondence not only would contain more letters of philosophical content from Mead, but revealing letters about Hawaiian political affairs which Castle would have received as an influential newspaper editor.
A helpful list of the family members, their births and deaths, was found in the collection and is filed in Box 7, Folder 8.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Castle, Mabel Wing. Papers
Nef, Elinor Castle. Papers
Subject Headings
Castle, Henry Northrup, 1862-1895; Castle, Mabel Wing, 1864-1950; Castle, Samuel Northrup, 1808-1894; Mead, George Herbert, 1863-1931
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  - Calling cards, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorandum from Samuel Northrup Castle, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Education – Oahu College – Report card, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Education – Oberlin College – Essays, 1881 and undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Education – Oberlin College – Notebook containing notes on Evidences of Christianity, Zoology, Physiology, and Chemistry, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Education – Oberlin College – Essays, 1883 and undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education – Oberlin College – "The Limitations of Thought" – Manuscripts and typescript, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Education – Oberlin College – Address on Hawaii, outline and typescript, circa 1883 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Education – Oberlin College – Class of 1883 List of Members, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Education – Harvard University Law School – Certificate of study, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Conditions and rules for Doctor of Philosophy at Friedrich-Wilhelms University, Berlin, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - European Journal, Volume 1 – Typescript, Summer 1879 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - European Journal, Volume 2 – Summer 1879 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Diary – "Chronicle of Events and Sensations, Thoughts and Feelings in Europe," 1879-1894 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bound typescript of "Chronicle of Events and Sensations, Thoughts and Feelings in Europe," includes typewritten copes of letters, 1879-1894 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - London hotel bill, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Guidebook to Lowestoft, England, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Signed consent for marriage to Frida Steckner, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Advertisement for lecture series, circa 1890 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Copy of article by Henry Northrup Castle in Hawaiian Gazette – "Robert Louis Stevenson's Letter," 1890 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings – Editorials written by Henry Northrup Castle for the Honolulu Advertiser, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Invitation to ball at Iolani Palace, circa 1892 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Certificate – Commissioner of Private Ways and Water Rights, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Police Constable's Commission, Island of Oahu, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings – Sinking of S.S. Elbe and death of Henry Northrup Castle and Dorothy Castle, 1895-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Elbe disaster clippings, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Broadside – Advertisement of rewards for recovery of victims of S.S. Elbe sinking, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Obituaries, February 1895 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Memorial, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - General – Incoming, 1884-1893 and undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General – Outgoing, 1885-1895 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Castle Family, unidentified individuals, 1875-1881 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Castle Family, General, 1872-1883 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Castle Family, General, 1886-1887 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Castle Family, General, 1888-1891 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Castle Family, General, 1893-1894 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Castle, Ida Mary Tenney, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Castle, James Bicknell, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Castle, James Bicknell, 1888-1889 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Castle, James Bicknell and Caroline Castle Westervelt, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1879-1882 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1885 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1886 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1889-1891 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907) and Harriet "Hattie" Castle Coleman, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1838-1926), 1878-1882 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894), 1880-1882 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894), 1885 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894), 1886 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894), 1888-1889 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894), 1893 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and James Bicknell Castle, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1882-1883 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1885 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1886-1887 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1888 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1889-1891 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894) and Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1893 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Castle, William Richards, 1872-1881 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Castle, William Richards, 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Castle, William Richards, 1889-1891 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Castle, William Richards, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Castle, William Richards, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Castle, William Richards and Ida Mary Tenney, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1873-1883 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1888-1891 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1893-1894 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Mead, George Herbert, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Mead, George Herbert, 1884-1885 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Mead, George Herbert, 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Mead, George Herbert, 1888 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Mead, George Herbert, 1892 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Mead, George Herbert and Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Mead, George Herbert and Helen Kingsbury Castle,1892-1894 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1876-1882 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1884-1885 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1886-1887 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1888-1891 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Thompson, Mary J., 1881-1883 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Thompson, Mary J., 1884-1885 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Thompson, Mary J., 1886-1887 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Thompson, Mary J.,1888-1891 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle, 1876-1882 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle, 1886-1887 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle, 1888-1891 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle and Helen Kingsbury Castle Mead, 1879-1881 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle and James Bicknell Castle, 1887 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series III: Castle Family Correspondence
  - Castle Family, General, 1893-1895 and undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Letters of condolence following death of Henry Northrup Castle, January-February 1895 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Letters of condolence following death of Henry Northrup Castle, February 1895 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Letters of condolence following death of Henry Northrup Castle, March 1895 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Castle, George Parmelee, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Castle, James Bicknell, 1888-1895 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, 1893-1895 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, 1892-1896 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, 1897-1900 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, 1901-1927 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Castle, Mabel Wing, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Castle, Mary Tenney (1819-1907), 1874-1897 and undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Castle, Samuel Northrup (1808-1894), 1888-1889 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Castle, William Richards, 1888-1895 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Coleman, Harriet "Hattie" Castle, 1865-1898 and undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Hitchcock, Henry Rowe (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mead, George Herbert, 1895-1901 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1885-1894 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, 1895-1909 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Mead, Helen Kingsbury Castle, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Steckner, Frida, 1889 and undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Swing, Elizabeth, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Tenney, Levi, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Westervelt, Caroline Castle, 1876-1904 and undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Castle Family Papers
  - List of Castle Family, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Frida Steckner Castle – Death notice, 1890 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - George Parmelee Castle – Clipping, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Mabel Wing Castle – Notes and Ephemera, 1888-1893 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mary Tenney Castle (1819-1907) – Obituaries, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Samuel Northrup Castle (1808-1894) – Obituaries, July 1894 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Hair, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Series V: Publication of Letters
  - Helen Castle Mead. "Recollections" (published), undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - George Herbert Mead. "Recollections" (published), undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - HNC, letters, typed copies, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - HNC, letters, typed copies, undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Letters. First page proof, photo proofs, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Letters. Marked second page proof, 1902 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Series VI: Photographs
  - Henry Northrup Castle and Dorothy Castle, 1884 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Castle Family photographs, 1895 and undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Series VII: Oversize
  - Letters. Marked galley proofs (Box 9, Folder 1)